{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "ï»¿Abraham Thomas Lincoln (February 12, 1809 â April 15, 1865) was an American statesman, politician, and lawyer who served as the 16th president of the United States from 1861 until his assassination in April 1865.", "entity": [["ï»¿Abraham", "NORP"], ["Thomas Lincoln", "PERSON"], ["February 12, 1809", "DATE"], ["April 15, 1865", "DATE"], ["American", "NORP"], ["16th", "ORDINAL"], ["the United States", "GPE"], ["1861", "DATE"], ["April 1865", "DATE"]]},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "Lincoln led the nation through the American Civil War, its bloodiest war and its greatest moral, constitutional, and political crisis.", "entity": [["Lincoln", "ORG"], ["the American Civil War", "ORG"]]},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "He preserved the Union, abolished slavery, strengthened the federal government, and modernized the U.S. economy.\n\n", "entity": [["Union", "ORG"], ["U.S.", "GPE"]]},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "Born in Kentucky, Lincoln grew up on the frontier in a poor family.", "entity": [["Kentucky", "GPE"], ["Lincoln", "ORG"]]},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "Self-educated, he became a lawyer, Whig Party leader, state legislator and Congressman.", "entity": [["Whig Party", "ORG"]]},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "He left government to resume his law practice, but angered by the success of Democrats in opening the prairie lands to slavery, reentered politics in 1854.", "entity": [["Democrats", "NORP"], ["1854", "DATE"]]},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "He became a leader in the new Republican Party and gained national attention in 1858 for debating and losing to national Democratic leader Stephen A. Douglas in a Senate campaign.", "entity": [["Republican Party", "ORG"], ["1858", "DATE"], ["Democratic", "NORP"], ["Stephen A. Douglas", "PERSON"], ["Senate", "ORG"]]},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "He then ran for President in 1860, sweeping the North and winning.", "entity": [["1860", "DATE"], ["North", "LOC"]]},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "Southern pro-slavery elements took his win as proof that the North was rejecting the Constitutional rights of Southern states to practice slavery.", "entity": [["North", "LOC"], ["Constitutional", "LAW"], ["Southern", "NORP"]]},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "They began the process of seceding from the union.", "entity": []},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "To secure its independence, the new Confederate States of America fired on Fort Sumter, one of the few U.S. forts in the South.", "entity": [["Confederate States of America", "GPE"], ["Fort Sumter", "GPE"], ["one", "CARDINAL"], ["U.S.", "GPE"], ["South", "LOC"]]},{"id": "AbrahamLincoln.txt", "sentence": "Lincoln called up volunteers and militia to suppress the rebellion and restore the Union.\n\n", "entity": [["Lincoln", "ORG"], ["Union", "ORG"]]},